<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life and death of Gamaliell Ratsey a famous theefe of England, executed at Bedford the 26. of March last past, 1605.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10473</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20753</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102571</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838343</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838343</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2718</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10473)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2718)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1115:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life and death of Gamaliell Ratsey a famous theefe of England, executed at Bedford the 26. of March last past, 1605.</title>
                  <author>Ratsey, Gamaliel, d. 1605. Repentance.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>V. Simmes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴(-F4).</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Includes: "Ratseys repentance which he wrote with his owne hand when hee was in New-gate", in verse, with caption title.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through; some pages stained; title page lacking (title taken from A2).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ratsey, Gamaliel, d. 1605.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE Life and death of Gamaliell <hi>Ratſey, a famous theefe of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, executed at Bedford the 26. of March laſt paſt, 1605.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N a Towne in Lincolne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire called <hi>Market-Deeping,</hi> lately dwelt a man inri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, as well in the vertues of his wife, as in the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his owne condition. For hee was generous both by birth and other perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the minde, which made him more fortunate in the loue of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, then in the comfort of his children. Carefull hee was for their education, and very induſtrious to giue them that bringing vp, that might either anſwer his hope, or be likely to yéelde them honeſt meanes of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and preferment. His name was <hi>Richard Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey,</hi> a Gentleman, and belonging to ſome honorable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage of this land, whom he followed a long time in great fauour and eſtimation. Amongſt his other chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="tcp:2718:3"/>he had one ſon named <hi>Gamaliel R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> of whom in his yong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r yeares, he conceiued a very hopefull expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for his care was great to bring him vp in learning and the knowledge of good letters. Wherein at the firſt he profited not a little, while he liued in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare and reprehenſion of his parents, and the awfull correction of his teacher. But as,
<q>
                  <l>Imberbis iuuenis tandem Cuſtode remoto</l>
                  <l>Gauaet equi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns, &amp; aperei gramine Campi, &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
So this <hi>Gamaliell Ratſey</hi> growing more mature and ripe in yeares and hauing that hand of reſtraint carried more looſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſie then was accuſtomed, by which he was formerly curbd of ſome libertie, grew leſſe duteous and more d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſirous to range abroad, &amp; ſee ſtrange Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, holding his hopes fruſtrated and himſelfe diſpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by liuing at home: and therefore reſolued to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the life and exerciſes of a Scholler, and betake him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the fortunes and profeſſion of a Souldier. As you ſhall heere vnderſtand by the courſe of his life, the which he related to ſome friends of his after the time of his impriſonment, with d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſire it might be publiſhed, as well to teſtifie vnto the world his repentance, as to giue cawſion to his country-men, to eſchew his follie, and preuent his fall. The which is further manifeſted in the end héereof, by his repentance written in his time of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance with his owne hand.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2718:3"/>
               <head>How <hi>Gamaliell Ratſey</hi> firſt left to bee a Scholler and became a Souldier.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Herefore I firſt thought good to make knowne, that at the time that the right honourable the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> went into <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> this <hi>Gamaliell Ratſey</hi> ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured his fortunes ouer with him, being at that time very young, and vnſkilfull in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of any Martiall affaires: yet hee ſpent much time in thoſe warres, and was very venturous and hote-ſpirited, and profited not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, as well in knowledge, as in the commendations of his Commanders: For in any publike deſignes or ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, he was not ſlacke to ſhew forwardneſſe, and in any priuate quarrell, very reſolute to repell iniuries. Inſomuch, as in thoſe parts he was then thought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy from a priuate Gentleman of a Company to bée made Sergeant. Which place hée remained in vnder the Company of Captaine <hi>Langford,</hi> till the time that my Lord of <hi>Deuonſhire</hi> came out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and brought ouer <hi>Tyrone,</hi> after the death of our late Soueraigne La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2718:4"/>
               <head>How <hi>Ratſey</hi> firſt fell into theft, by what meanes, and in what place, and how he was impriſoned in <hi>Spalding,</hi> with his dangerous eſcape out of priſon in his ſhirt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the Earle of <hi>Deuonſhires</hi> returne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Ratſey</hi> came like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe backe againe, &amp; ſhaped his courſe through the Country, homewards to the place where he was borne, where it is booteleſſe to tell what pranckes hee performed in his iourney. But this at his arriuall at home, though it was firſt, yet was it not the leaſt of his exploites, for he gulld the ſeruant, deceiued the maiſter, and eſcaped for that time out of priſon. But as <hi>Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry euill act hath his euill end:</hi> ſo his ſucceſſe was ſo hard, that he was croſt almoſt to the croſſe, and that is the next neighbour to the gallowes; and <hi>miſerere mei,</hi> had beene the beſt mattens, had not one paire of legges been better then two paire of hands.</p>
               <p>For thus it fortuned, that not long after his comming home out of Ireland, he went to a Market towne cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Spalding, not farre from the place where hee was borne, where comming into an Inne in the ſame towne, he inſinuated himſelfe into the loue and league of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, Maid in the ſame houſe, with whom he preuailed ſo farre, what with his pleaſing ſpeach (and with what elſe he pleaſed her I know not) that hee was the onely man in the maides eſtimation. Inſomuch that in his abſence (for he was comming and going thither often) the Maide preuailed ſo with her Miſtreſſe, that hée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any other gueſt ſhould bee admitted the priuiledge
<pb facs="tcp:2718:4"/>of the Parlour. But as had-I-wiſt comes too late, and kindneſſe oftentimes receiues not her deſerued effects. So fell it out in this his ſo ſodaine intertainment: for he only made that his mean to awaite ſome oportunitie, when he might ſpie out a purchaſe and effect his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as it ſhortly after fell out he did.</p>
               <p>For a Farmer, or huſband-man, comming to the ſame Inne (as it was his cuſtome vpon Market dayes) to pay a matter of fortie pounds to a Gentleman dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling there, which was due vpon a bond, called the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſſe aſide, and deſired her, that ſhe would lay vp the ſame ſafe for him (being ſealed vp in a bagge) till the Market was done, which ſhee receyued, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to doe accordingly. And comming into the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor where <hi>Ratſey</hi> remained, ſhe ſhewed herſelfe nothing ſqueamiſh to ſhew what truſt was repoſed in her: but locking the ſame in a Preſſe, he thought (that her backe once turned) hee would diſcharge her of that charge. For as hee had an Eagles eye to eſpie aduauntage, ſo had he a Lions heart to effect his purpoſe: for hée was not long hammering it in his head, but with a quicke diſpatch, vnlocked the Preſſe, and pocketted the bagge. Which when he had got, it was booteleſſe to bid him haſte away: for he preſently bade them farewell in the Inne for a while, and told them hée would but walke into the market, and come againe by and by, although he meant nothing leſſe, and they miſtruſted nothing at all. But hée hied home to <hi>Deeping,</hi> where in his Mothers Orchard, hee digged a pitte, and buried the bagge of money, doubting there would bee ſearch made after him for it, and not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>g found about him, or in his mothers houſe, it would be out their yea, and his nay, and ſo the matter might hee the more eaſily aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2718:5"/>
               <p>Now you muſt imagine, that the market béeing done, and the Farmer calling for his bagge of money, and the Hoſteſſe finding that the ſame was taken out of the Cupboord, and her Preſſe opened, was not a little perplexed in minde, but it ſtroke ſuch a quanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to her ſtomacke, as if ſhée had drunke a draught of ſmall beere next her heart in a feoſtie morning. Shee came backe to the Farmer, with her handes emptie, and her heart full of cares, exclayming agaynſt <hi>Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey,</hi> whome ſhée remembred ſhee left in the Parlour, but that auayled nothing. Thereupon they both went to a Iuſtice of Peace dwelling neere <hi>Spalding,</hi> and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their ſayde griefes and loſſes, deſired his warrant to bring <hi>Ratſey</hi> before him, which hee graunted, and they procured to bée ſerued by a Conſtable of <hi>Deeping.</hi> So <hi>Ratſey</hi> béeing apprehended, and brought before the Iuſtice, ſtoode ſtiffely in the deniall thereof, and was committed to the ſafe keeping of the Gayler, vpon ſuſpition of felonie.</p>
               <p>Where he had not long remained, but money was wanting vnto him, and he had no meanes to relieue his neceſſities in priſon, but to reueale the hiding of the money in the ſayde Orchard, and therefore bethought him whome in ſuch a caſe hee might make the ſame knowne vnto, with his beſt ſecuritie. Wherevpon hée reſolued to make none acquainted therewithall, but his owne mother, to whom hee addreſſed ſecret knowledge thereof. Which when ſhee heard, ſhee was in a great perplexitie what to doe, whether ſhe ſhould proue vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall in reuealing the ſame, or by concealing it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard her reputation in the Countrey. In the which ſhe was alwayes verie well eſteemed with the moſt and beſt, both for wiſedome and vertue.</p>
               <p>His mother to be further aduiſed, reuealed it to
<pb facs="tcp:2718:5"/>her daughter dwelling in the ſame Towne, her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to her huſband, and ſo from one to another, (as <hi>two may keepe counſaile, if the third be away:</hi>) it came to the Iuſtices hearing, where, and in what place, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what trée in the Orchard it was hidden.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ratſey</hi> hauing ſecret information of notice giuen to the Iuſtice, and that he ſhould be further examined con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame, knew that deniall would not then ſerue his turne, but reſolued to ſet all his wits abroach, to frée himſelfe from their hands, which could by no meanes bee done, but by eſcape, which he effected in a morning betimes, out of a very narrow paſſage in his ſhirt.</p>
               <p>But the time was not long after his eſcape before he was miſſed, and haſt made after him on euery ſide, both by horſe and foote. He was egerly purſued, yet knew the Country well; and was a long ſpace followed ſo hardly, that he was at laſt forced to a very dangerous great wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which he tooke and ſwamme ouer; and being ouer, he ſtaid and turned himſelfe towards them, and after ſome brauadoes giuen them, (for he knew none of them durſt follow him) he went his way and out-ſtript them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A kinde conceipt of <hi>Ratſey,</hi> performed by him in his way vpon a Seruing-man that ouer-tooke him by chance, riding to <hi>London</hi> with his Maiſters horſe to fetch him from the Tearme.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter he had made this eſcape, hée tooke his way to a friend of his not farre off, with whom hee might bee bolde for ſute of apparrel, and to furniſh him with ſuch neceſſaries as his caſe required. The
<pb facs="tcp:2718:6"/>which his friend furniſhed him withall, and put ſome ſmall matter of money into his purſe to beare his char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, for he knew as ſoone as <hi>Ratſey</hi> had ſtrooke a hand, he ſhould be no loſer by it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ratſey,</hi> as a man then halfe armed to enterpriſe any exploit, and well fleſht by his late eſcape, tooke his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney on towards <hi>London,</hi> thinking there to finde men of all faculties, and copeſ-mates to fit his humour in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery condition. For although by the great diſcretion of the Iudges and Iuſtices, many are daily truſſed vp, yet ſtill there ſpringeth vp yong that grow, in time, to beare fruit fit for the gallowes.</p>
               <p>As hée had thus trauailed two or thrée daies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes <hi>London,</hi> booted and ſpurrd, and afoote, hee turning backe to breathe himſelfe, being wearie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpied a Seruing-man riding after him with a ſpare nagge, for hée ledde his owne horſe in his hande, and roade vppon his Maiſters Gelding; which good opportunitie was ſoone apprehended by <hi>Ratſey,</hi> for hée preſentlie beganne to call his wittes about him, and to bethinke him howe hee might ouer-reach the plaine ſeruing creature that followed him. Who no ſooner ouer-tooke him, but hée ſtraitway vailde his bonnet at the ſight of Maiſter <hi>Ratſey;</hi> who ſeeing the young Nouice ſo full of curteſſe, reſolued to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay him with craft ere they parted. For <hi>Ratſey</hi> fell preſentlie a queſtioning with him, if hée didde not ouer-goe a Seruing-man leading a Gelding (as hee did) in his hand? who made him anſwer, that he met not any ſuch. Then <hi>Ratſey</hi> beganne to faine himſelfe in a fuſtian ſume, and ſwore his man ſhould neither carry it to hell nor heauen for abuſing him ſo, for I bade him follow mee (ſaith hee) and he ſure miſtooke mee, thinking I would ride to ſuch a Gentlemans to night,
<pb facs="tcp:2718:6"/>and hath ſo left me as thou ſéeſt. But if thou béeſt an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt fellow (quoth hee) let me ride vpon thy léere horſe and I will giue thée a couple of ſhillings to drinke. The ſéely fellow gréedie of two ſhillings, (for it was a great deale of money in his purſe) and ſéeming to be ſory that ſuch an honeſt Gentleman (as he thought) ſhould goe a foote and he a ſpace horſe in his hand, gaue his good will, which <hi>Ratſey</hi> tooke hold of, and preſently mounted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. So they roade a great part of the day together, paſſing the way with much idle prattle. But yet <hi>Ratſey</hi> was not ſatiſfied in his minde, that the Seruingman ſhould ride vppon the beſt Gelding, and not hee, and reſolued to haue a fling at him for that too.</p>
               <p>So the afternoone being well ſpent, and night drawing on, <hi>Ratſey</hi> beganne to betake himſelfe to his firſt diſcontent, and roade a prettie way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any chat or prattle, as hee hadde before. Which the ſimple Seruing-man perceiuing, thought hee would chéere him vppe alitle, and beganne to aſke him how hée did, and what ayled him: <hi>Ratſey</hi> told him his mans negligence ſtucke ſtill in his ſtomacke, and hée could not forget it. For ſaith hée, I am now néere the place where I intende to lie all night, and I haue many worſhipfull friendes and kinſfolkes there, and it grieues mee to the heart, that I ſhould bee ſéene come riding into the Towne in ſuch a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion and ſo meanelie horſed, for I tell thee (friend ſaieth hee) I neuer came thither without my man or twoo with mee, and a very good Gelding vnder mee.</p>
               <p>The Seruingman hearing this, told him, if that were al if his Maſters gelding would pleaſure him, he ſhould ride on that, and hee would change horſes with him.
<pb facs="tcp:2718:7"/>Yes mary quoth <hi>Ratſey,</hi> (for he aimed at that) for I hold thy Maiſters Gelding to be worth ſome twentie ponnd: he coſt not a penny leſſe, quoth the Seruingman. So they interchange horſes, and riding on, <hi>Ratſey</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded him, ſéeing he had béen thus kind, to do him one other pleaſure, and he would pay for his horſe meate and mans meate that night, and ſet him forth frée in the morning, with ſomewhat in his purſe to drinke. The Seruingman aſked of him what it was; nothing (ſaies he) but to lie at my Inne too night, and be to me as my man, and I will reward thy paines, for thou ſhalt both ſaue thine owne charges, and continue my credite. That I will (ſaith he) with all my heart, and doe you the beſt ſeruice I can.</p>
               <p>So the ſéely fellow for that night became <hi>Ratſeys</hi> man, and comming to the Inne, the horſes were ſet vp, and he commanded his man to direct that ſupper ſhould bée prouided. Which being done, and ſupper ended, <hi>Ratſey</hi> goes into the ſtable, and giues order that his horſes be well dreſt and looked too. For (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aies he) my man is but new come to me, and I dare not as yet truſt him with dreſſing my Gelding, which the Oſtlers promiſed to do accordingly. And perceiuing the gentleman to be a kind man, they thought they would doe ſome kindneſſe to his ſeruant in the bottome of the Seller. For while <hi>Ratſey</hi> was playing at dice aboue, with ſome others that were there, his new man was carowſing below. And wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that <hi>vim etentiuam,</hi> and abilitie that the reſt had to carry their liquor, he beganne to fell Dakes in the Tap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, and his beſt braines were wrapt in a leaden cap: for he was ſo heauie in the head, that he could not ſtand on his feete. So he was had to bed preſently.</p>
               <p>It fitted <hi>Ratſeys</hi> purpoſe well, that while hée loſt his money at Dice, his man did gaine his loading with
<pb facs="tcp:2718:7"/>drinke, for hee had an intention to ſende him away on foote, and ſo he did. For by that they had done playing, the morning beganne to waxe gray, and hée fell a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayning for his beſt Gelding with the Hoſt of the houſe, and receyued ninetéene pounds for him. Who was no leſſe glad of the one, then <hi>Ratſey</hi> was of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So he diſcharged the houſe, and commaunded his mans Nag to be ſadled for him, (while he was all this while aſleepe.)</p>
               <p>Which being done, he left ſome ſmall matter of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney behind him for his man, and gaue order that hee ſhould follow him to ſuch a Gentlemans houſe, where he neuer meant to méete him, and ſo rode his way.</p>
               <p>Now what a ſorrowfull and troubled heart this yong Nouice had, when he roſe and found his new mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter gone with his old maiſters Geldings, I referre to to them that haue grieued at the like loſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How <hi>Ratſey</hi> met <hi>George Snell,</hi> and <hi>Henrie Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſe,</hi> and of their riding togither in North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamtonſhire, and his robbing of nine men alone.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Atſey</hi> reſolued after his late purchaſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to buy houſe or land with his xix. li. but ſéeking for copſmates of his owne condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that were as readie to liue vppon ſpoile as himſelfe: at laſt her met with <hi>Shorthoſe</hi> an old friend and Countrey-man of his (for <hi>Shorthoſe</hi> was likewiſe borne in Market-deeping.) And although <hi>Shorthoſe</hi> (till hee perſwaded him) neuer gaue conſent to enter into anie malefaction, but was driuen for matter of debt to forſake his natiue
<pb facs="tcp:2718:8"/>countrey. Yet being very poore hee was glad of <hi>Ratſeys</hi> companie, and holpe him to ſpend a great part of his money ſo lately, and ſo lewdly got, which in a little ſpace drew néere an end, (for two hands in one pocket ſoone makes a light purſe.)</p>
               <p>Then came they both in companie by chaunce with <hi>Snell,</hi> whome <hi>Ratſey</hi> perceiued, as well by conference, as by countenance, (as <hi>Quam difficile eſt animam non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere vultu</hi>) as apt to incline to deſperate courſes, as themſelues, (as indeede hee had beene before,) for hée was twice burnt in the hand in Newgate for his bad conditions.</p>
               <p>Well: they all layde their heades togither, and foorth they went, although none horſed but <hi>Ratſey,</hi> and layde theyr plottes for Northamtonſhire, and thoſe partes, for there hée was moſt ſkilfull of the Countrey: and comming to a place called <hi>Helpſon</hi>-heath, they eſpyed nine men riding towards them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that were bound for London. <hi>Ratſey</hi> reſolued to ſhew his reſolution vppon them, and bade his other companions to goe on the infide of the Hedge into a cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pice, while he lay on the outſide cracking of Nuts: and bade the other not come forth vnleſſe they ſaw great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of their helpe.</p>
               <p>The men drew ſomewhat neere the place where <hi>Ratſey</hi> lay, and being within ſight of him, one of them knew him, (for they were all Lincolneſhire men) and bade the reſt bee reſolued to looſe their purſes now, for (ſayeth hee) yonder lyes <hi>Ratſey,</hi> whom I know to bee a daungerous and deſperate fellow, and he awaytes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a prey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ratſey</hi> makes roughly towardes them, and tolde them that he came for money, and money he muſt haue, and would haue: therefore diſpatch (quoth her) for one
<pb facs="tcp:2718:8"/>of your companie héere knowes me, and knowes I will not be trifled with.</p>
               <p>On our faythes (ſayde they) maiſter <hi>Ratſey,</hi> wee are no better prouided then will be are our charges to London, and that at the moſt is not twentie ſhillings a man, if you will haue that, you ſhall haue it with all our hearts. Nay (ſayes <hi>Ratſey</hi>) that will doe mee no good: for it is well knowne I robbe not for trifles. But what haue you ſir, ſayes hee to one that ſtoode aloofe from the reſt, in your Portmantgle? Fayth, ſayes hee, I haue a little money that I am to pay vppon bond by a day, and wee are two or three of vs heere bound to pay it, if you take it from vs wee are vndone. How much is it, ſayes <hi>Ratſey?</hi> Two hundred poundes (ſayes the other) I Marrie, quoth <hi>Ratſey,</hi> ſuch a lumpe I looke for. And ſeeing there are ſo many to pay it, it will not hurt you much if all of you looſe it. Therefore be briefe, deliuer it, for if you ſtand vppon tearmes, or delayes with mee, I haue Whelpes within the inſide of the Hedge, that vpon a Watch-worde will preſently come foorth, and they neuer barke till they bite: if they ſtirre, it is all thinges to nothing, but ſome of you looſe your liues, and your limmes. This beeing heard, the money was preſently deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for of two euils, they thought it beſt to chooſe the leaſt. And <hi>Ratſey,</hi> hee thought it the beſt cracking of Nuttes that euer he made, that yeelded ſuch ſhelles; And ſo they parted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2718:9"/>
               <head>How <hi>Ratſey</hi> robbed a Coniurer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Atſey</hi> had ſecrete notice giuen him of a Coniurer that was a maiſter of Artes, and a Scholler of Cambridge (for he had his intellegencers abroad, although a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtate of the Common-wealth) and was directed which way hee roade, with his bookes of coniuration in a Cloake-bag behinde him. But <hi>Ratſey</hi> thought all his bookes ſhould not ſaue him: for he meant to coniure him without booke, not ſo much for the money ſake (for he had knowledge that the Scholler had not aboue fiue or ſixe poundes aboute him.) But for that it ſhould be ſayd that he once in his life, his courage and ſpirit out-ſtript and daunted the cunning and arte of a Coniurer.</p>
               <p>For following him till hee came in <hi>Bawtrie</hi> Lane, where hee intended this exployte, and which indeede is a verie daungerous place for theeuing, <hi>Ratſey</hi> made towardes him, and the Coniurer thought a good paire of Spurres better than Spelles or Coniuration at that time, and beganne to pricke forwardes his Horſe, which indeede was ſo farre better then <hi>Ratſeys,</hi> that had not <hi>Shorthoſe</hi> ſtept in, who lay to preuent his eſcape, the Coniurer had out-rid <hi>Ratſey,</hi> and ſaued both his bookes and money.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2718:9"/>
               <p>But now the Coniurer is in huckſters handling, there is no wap with him but one, for <hi>Ratſey</hi> ſeiſes both vpon his money and bookes, for the which the Coniurer pleads hard, but prou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es not. And thinking his paine had béene paſt, be begins to take his leaue of maiſter <hi>Ratſey,</hi> and to ride away: nay ſayes <hi>Ratſey</hi> (and takes his horſe by the head) I haue not done with you yet; I haue a quarrell to this gallant too, he muſt goe with me, for preſuming to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne me: it may be you haue infuſde ſome Arte into your horſe, that may ſtand me in ſtéed hereafter, for I like him well at hand, howſoeuer he is at length. So the Coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers horſe went with <hi>Ratſey,</hi> which was an excellent good Gelding, for <hi>Ratſey</hi> was oftentimes offered xx. pound for him, which he refuſed, for he prooued ſo fit for his purpoſe, that all the prankes that <hi>Ratſey</hi> plaid afterwards, was vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Coniurers horſe.</p>
               <p>The Coniurer he walkes now a foote, and had he not had two or thrée péeces of golde left in a ſecret place, which <hi>Ratſey</hi> found not, I thinke he would with <hi>Batillus</hi> haue hangd himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How Ratſey robd a Scholler of Cambridge, and cauſde him make an Oration to him in a Wood.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Atſey another time riding by the way, and <hi>Snell</hi> and <hi>Shorthoſe</hi> with him, (for they ſtill ſerued for his men, vnleſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the performance of any exploit) met with a Scholler, that had béene to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a part of his wiues dowrie which was foure ſcore pound and vpwards: And <hi>Ratſey</hi> pretending his courſe the ſame way that the Scholler did, they rode together a great while, they paſt away the time with much talke of many matters. And
<pb facs="tcp:2718:10"/>the Scholler (thinking at leaſt he had béene in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of a Knights ſoune and heire, for that <hi>Ratſey</hi> rode with his two men, one before, and another behinde) began to diſcourſe of many former accidents, and after fell into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the iniquitie of the time, the corruptions of mens conditions, and the obduracie &amp; hardneſſe of their hearts, for (ſaith the Scholler) it is a world to ſée how little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard is now a dayes had of Schollers and Souldiers, how they range in euery corner without reſpect, or reliefe. Their diſtreſſe is in euery mans eie, but out of euery mans heart, ſo that our preſent times make good that old ſaying:
<q>Charitas laudatur at alget.</q>
With much other prattle to this effect: which <hi>Ratſey</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ſoothed vp a pritty while, till he came to a conuenient place, néere a wood ſide, and then whiſtled, and both his men came about the Scholler, for the whiſtle was a watchword betwéene them, which when he ſaw, he was in a pittifull plight, and <hi>Ratſey</hi> ſpake to him thus, or to this effect. Now honeſt Scholler, for ſo thy talke and thy habit ſhewes thée to be; know we are not as we ſéeme, for we are Gentlemen and Souldiours, ſuch as thou didſt talke of before: we are in want, and we ſcorne to crye out our wants in the ſtréets, for we ſhall not be heard; we will haue money if it walke vpon the earth. And therefore to be ſhort, you muſt néeds miniſter your purſe to me preſently. Come diſpatch, make no delay, for we cannot tarry. This ſtroke cold to the ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers heart, for he little thought that the ſpéech he made would produce ſuch effect. But ſéeing he perceiued there was no remedie, but he muſt néeds vntruſſe (for he ſaw they were all reſolute) he quietly deliuered his money vnto them, and would haue beene gone.</p>
               <p>Nay ſayes <hi>Ratſey</hi> you muſt néeds ſtay with me a little, for I muſt talke a word or two with you in yonder Wood: The Scholler fearing if he had him there, he would binde
<pb facs="tcp:2718:10"/>him, and do him ſome bodily harme, fell on his knées, and deſired him to be good vnto him; Riſe vp man, ſayes <hi>Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey,</hi> come I meane not to hurt thée, I would but haue thy counſaile in a matter. Well, when they were in the wood together, <hi>Ratſey</hi> told him, that he lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d his diſcourſe ſo well at firſt, and ſped ſo well after it, that he was deſtrous he ſhould preach vnto him ſome ſhort Sermon of Repentance, for ſayes he, I haue béene a long malefactor, and it may ſo preuaile with me, that it may worke me to ſome good déeds, after my many euils. The Scholler knew he muſt néeds do as he would haue him, now being in his hands, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtept to a Trée, choſe his text to that effect, and made a ſpeach of halfe an houre long: which being ended, <hi>Ratſey</hi> gaue him a brace of Angels back of his money, and tolde him if euer he came to be a Lord, he would make him his Chaplaine for his labour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How he robd two men, and Knighted them.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Gamaliell Ratſey,</hi> &amp; his two other compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, <hi>Snell</hi> &amp; <hi>Shorthoſe,</hi> hauing laine two or thrée dayes in an Inne in <hi>Stamford,</hi> expecting ſome booty worthy the taking; At laſt there came into the ſame Inne where they lay, two men that had forty pounds a péece about them, and were ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into Lincolnſhire to buy wool, which when they heard, they were not a little glad of, for they made account it was their owne ſtraight, &amp; dealt with the Chamberlaine of the houſe to learne which way they rode in the morning, which the chamberlaine performed accordingly &amp; that with great care &amp; diligence, for he knew he ſhould partake of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and ſhare with them, if they ſped. So they were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by him, which way the two men did intend their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell in the morning.</p>
               <p>The morning being come, the Chamberlaine gaue them ſuch an hunteſ-vp, as made them riſe preſently, for;
<pb facs="tcp:2718:11"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Quid non mortalia pectora cogit</l>
                     <l>Auri ſacra fames?</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>They ſlept not ſoundly that night, till the thirſty deſire of their purchaſe was effected. Vp t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey got with all ſpeede, and gaue order that their horſes ſhould be made readie, which being in readineſſe, they rode eaſily before the ſame way that the Chamberlein directed them, for they imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the two men would not follow them in an hower, or two after. But they made too much haſt for their little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for they had not ſtayed one whole hower, when they might eſpie the two Clothiers fiue miles beiond <hi>Stamford</hi> ryding towards <hi>Lyncolne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And at Fiue mile Croſſe, <hi>Ratſey</hi> gaue them ſuch a good morrow, as with fowre wordes ſpeaking, (<hi>Stande, deliuer your purſe</hi>) he fetcht foureſcore pounds from them at one clappe. This being done, he had them knéele downe &amp; draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth his weapon, he aſked them what their ſeuerall names were, and of what profeſſion. They told him, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweared they were Woolmen by trade, <hi>Ratſey</hi> then laying his weapon on the ſhoulder of one of them had him riſe vp <hi>Sir Walter Woolſack,</hi> &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other riſe vp <hi>Sir Samuell Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skinne.</hi> You are now (ſaies he) both my knights, as I haue many others beſides you; that haue payd mee their ſeuerall fées, according to their abilities, as you haue done, for their election into the order of Knighthood: If any aſke you who beſtowed that dignity vpon you, ſaye you mette with <hi>K. Ratſey,</hi> and ſo farewell.</p>
               <p>Thus they rid away, and left the two Woolmen heauie in heart and emptie in purſe, and how little they ioyed in their poore Knighthood ſo richly paid for. Let euery in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different opinion iudge by himſelfe, as if he had beene in their taking.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2718:11"/>
               <head>How Ratſey dealt with a poore man going to a Market, whom he intended to haue robd.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nother time <hi>Ratſey</hi> ryding betweene <hi>Huntington</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> (for he kept for the moſt part in thoſe parts) he mette with an old Man going to S. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lves</hi> to a faire, And thinking he had had more ſtore of monie about him, he began to be briefe with the old Man, and his wife (for ſhe was likewiſe in his company) and to tell them that he lackt money, it was a hard time for men of his profeſſion, there were no warres, and Souldiers had no imployments. Therefore (father ſayes he) I muſt haue your money, I come for it, be ſhort and deliuer it. The old man hee ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſhaking as if a man had bene giuing vp the ghoſt. And told him that in all world hee had but fiue nobles and that he was faine to make hard ſhift for, and ſell ſome of his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſtuffe to make it vp, and if he ſhould die hee left not one penny at home to helpe him, and my wife (ſaies he) hath but one Edward ſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ling and a Mill ſixpence, which hath ſeene no ſunne theſe ſeauen yeares, and that ſhe hath taken in her purſe if we ſhould want money, and all this we haue pacht vpp togeather (maiſter) to buye vs one cow to keepe me and my wife now we are old. If you take if from vs we are vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly vndone. You are an old diſſembler (Sirra ſaies <hi>Ratſey</hi> to him, I haue met with ſuch as you that haue ſaid as much as you doe, and yet I haue found more ſiluer and gold in a ruſſet hoſe then in veluet breeches.</p>
               <p>It may be ſo quoth the old Man, but on my faith and hollidome I deale truly with you ſir. And with that he drew forth his leather purſe, and powred forth his ſtore, and his wife hers, and badde him euen deale with them, as hee would.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2718:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ratſey</hi> ſeeing this was true, tooke the monies of both of them, but returned it backe, and told them hee had too high a mind to looke vpon ſo low a matter, and therewithal gaue the old Man Forty ſhillings out of his owne purſe, and bad him by a couple of kine: for I hold it worſe then Sacriledge (ſayes <hi>Ratſey</hi>) to rob the ſpittle, and while I liue the Sermon in the wood muſt teach me to fauour and pitie them that are poore, and helpe them, for the rich can helpe themſelues.</p>
               <p>Thus did <hi>Ratſey</hi> leaue the old Man both lighter at heart, and heauier in purſe then he found him, but how honeſt a theefe the old Man thought him to be when hee was gone, let euery poore Man iudge, that lackes a Cowe &amp; hath fortie ſhillings giuen him to buy one.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How Ratſey got 300. poundes in one night by his venture of 50. pounds with a farmer, that he neuer ſaw til they met together in an Inne.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T fortuned that <hi>Ratſey,</hi> and his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lying at an Inne in New Market, there came into the ſame houſe a farmer, or huſbandman by occaſion of buſineſſe that way, who intending to lye there all night, and being alone, demaunded of the Hoſte, if there were no companie with whom he might ſuppe, he made him anſwere that he had no gueſts that night, but one Gentleman and his Men, and he knew not whether he would permitte any ſtraunger to ſuppe with him, but (ſaies the Hoſt) I will aſke of him. So <hi>Ratſeys</hi> pleaſure being damaunded in that caſe, he was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent: for it was an accident that fitted his expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that lay there to no other end, but to awaite opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: &amp; it was a good wind he thought that would blow him ſome profit.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2718:12"/>
               <p>Then <hi>Ratſeys</hi> ſupper being ready, the ſtraunger was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to his chamber, where the cloath was laid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>Ratſey</hi> gaue him a kinde welcome, though with a Iewiſh heart, (for he meant to rob him, though indeede it ſell out other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) So they fat downe, &amp; <hi>Ratſeys</hi> two ſuppoſed ſeruing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, waited as dutifully, as if they had had a Maiſter of a better condition. But all ſupper time the farmer vſed verie few words, was diſcontent, and very heauie at heart, which he could not but diſcouer, which <hi>Ratſey</hi> perceiuing, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him the cauſe of his ſo great griefe and melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which with much adoe he told him.</p>
               <p>The truth is, ſaith the farmer, I haue much cauſe of griefe, and for my life I cannot diſſemble it, it tour heth me ſo néere; For to morrow I am to paie two hundred pounds to a Gentleman not farre from hence which I am bound to diſcharge, and more then my bond, my houſe, and land is morgaged vnto him, and I remaine at his mircie, for I haue had ſuch loſſes and hindrances, that all I can make amounts but to one hundred and fifty pounds, &amp; I &amp; mine are vtterly vndone, vnles I can take new order for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the other fiftie pounds by a day, which I am very doubtfull of; he is reported to be ſo cruell, and vnconſciona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>If this be all (ſayes <hi>Ratſey</hi>) be of good chéere, for although my ſelfe am vnknowne vnto him, yet I am ſure he hath heard of my friends, for they are not dwelling farre from him: And I will do ſo much for you as to ride with you in the morning to him, and doubt not I will preuaile, that he ſhall forbeare you till a further time, without forfeiture or aduantage taken: for I preſume one gentleman will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny another ſuch a requeſt being ſo neere neigh bors.</p>
               <p>The Farmer gaue him great thanks, &amp; was well comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by that promiſe, for it ſéemed a very likly thing, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that ſhew that <hi>Ratſey</hi> was of, might both perſwade
<pb facs="tcp:2718:13"/>and preuailed with his creditor. So ſupper ended, they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their ſeuerall todgings and the poore man was much merrier by this hope conceiued.</p>
               <p>Well, morning being come, they rode altogether accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to promiſe, and as they rode, ſtill <hi>Ratſey</hi> would faine haue béene dooing with this hundred and fiftie pound, but (as God would haue it) his purpoſe was ſtill croft by the continuall comming too and fro of paſſengers, who made <hi>Ratſey</hi> at that time <hi>volens nolens,</hi> to play the true man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will. But he thought he would goe through ſtitch now, as he had beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nne, and indéed (although at firſt he neuer meant it, when he ſayd it) rode with the Farmer to the Gentleman his houſe, where <hi>Ratſey</hi> as well as he could playd the Rhetoritian, to perſwade the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to beare with his debtor for a time for the odde fiftie pounds &amp; told him, if either he or any friend of his had cauſe to vſe him, or his meanes, where he dwelt, (for he tooke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the name of a Gentlemans ſonne ſome xx. miles fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence of great reckoning) he ſhould commaund him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite his courteſie. Sir, ſaid the Gentleman<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I haue no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with your father but this I haue heard, that he is a man of great worth &amp; worſhip in the country, and could I without my great preiudice, pleaſure this man at your requeſt, it is as like you might obtaine it at my hands, as any man liuing to whom I am not further engag'd. But beléeue me ſir, as I am a Gentleman, I am to ride to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to pay <hi>300.</hi> pound for a purchace, &amp; my credit is bound for it, &amp; I haue ſo depended vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the paiment of this money, as I haue neglected to prouide for my ſelfe otherwiſe, vpon the aſſurance of it. Therfore you muſt néeds ercuſe me, and ſo turnd his back, and was going away Nay ſtay ſir ſayes <hi>Ratſey,</hi> I will once in my life play the Marchant venturer, and hazard fifty pounds vpon a man I neuer ſaw before: Oh ſir, ſayes the man (and ſell vpon his knées) if you will
<pb facs="tcp:2718:13"/>do this pleaſure to a ſtranger, you ſhall binde me, my wife, and children to pray for you, and I will be as carefull to make you reſtitution, as I am now deſirous to be helpt in this extremity: and I hope you ſhall not ſtay long for your mony. <hi>Ratſey</hi> made that reckoning ſoo, for he intended to be paid at ſome of their hands before they parted. To be ſhort, <hi>Ratſey</hi> tendered downe fifty pounds in gold preſently in the mans behalfe, which the Gentleman receiued, &amp; was ſo wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceited of <hi>Ratſey,</hi> that he made them al his gueſts y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night.</p>
               <p>The night being paſt ouer, and the morning come, the Gentleman of the houſe gat vp, &amp; bagd the thrée hundreth pounds, and made himſelfe ready for his buſineſſe, &amp; to ride: <hi>Ratſey</hi> was not long after, before he was as ready as he, for he meant to accompany him which way ſoeuer he rode, So breakfaſt being paſt, <hi>Ratſey</hi> tolde the Gentleman he would ride ſome part of his way with him, as he pretended occaſion of buſineſſe, which the Gentleman was very glad of, for he was ſo farre from any miſtruſt of him, (for that he nam'd himſelfe ſuch a Gentlemans ſonne) as he held him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe much grac'd by his company. The Farmer tooke his leaue of them both, and was not a little glad that he had eſcapt his late danger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ratſey</hi> and the Gentleman had not rode many miles to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, when the Gentlemans mans horſe (for he carried the thrée hundred pounds in a Port-mantle behinde him) began to faint, being a graſſe Nagge, and they were much troubled with him; which <hi>Ratſey</hi> perceiuing, had the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman (if he pleaſed) to let his man take it behind him (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing better horſt) as long as they rode together. The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman thanked him very heartily. So the money was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued, and ſet behind <hi>Shorthoſe.</hi> This was that which <hi>Ratſey</hi> aimd at, for now he knew his venture of fiftie pofids would come home with profit. <hi>Shorthoſe</hi> hauing the Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantle behinde him, néeded no directions what to doe, for
<pb facs="tcp:2718:14"/>their mindes were well enough knowne the one to the other. But as the Gentleman &amp; <hi>Ratſey</hi> paſt the time away with talke of many matters, little minding the way before them, ſo <hi>Shorthoſe</hi> by little and little mended his pace, and in very ſhort time gotte much ground of them, which the Gentleman perceiuing, told M. <hi>Ratſey</hi> that his man rode too faſt. Then <hi>Ratſey</hi> began to call and whiſtle to his man, but he would take no notice of it, but the more he calde or whiſtled, the more he ſtole away by degrées. At the which <hi>Ratſey</hi> ſéem'd much mou'd, and did ſweare and teare excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, and told the Geatleman that he would ride &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take him &amp; ſtay him with a vengeance, who all this while miſtruſted nothing, for <hi>Ratſeys</hi> aſſumption of ſuch a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s name, drownd the conceit of any doubts or ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>But being ridden after his man, <hi>Snell</hi> likewiſe begins to pace after his maiſter (as it was his duty) &amp; the faſter they followed <hi>Shorrhoſe,</hi> the faſter he rode from them ſo that in a little time as they grew néere together, and at a conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient place of changing the way, they raind their horſes back towards the old gentleman (who followed likewiſe as faſt as he could) and wau'd their harts ouer their heads as a farewell for his <hi>300.</hi> pound, and ſo rid cléere away. The Gentleman he made hue and crye after them, but to no purpoſe for they were ſo well horſt and ſo well experienced in euery by way, that at their pleaſure they would out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip a countrey.</p>
               <p>The Gentleman went about to trouble the Farmer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he brought him to his houſe but it auaild him nought, for he produc'd ſuch ſufficient proofe how they met by cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the Inne together, and was ſo well knowne to be of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt life and conuerſation, that any matter ſuggeſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, could not preuaile to his hurt.</p>
               <p>So the old Gentleman with his man return'd home by <hi>Weeping Croſſe,</hi> and all he had for his thrée hundreth
<pb facs="tcp:2718:14"/>pounds, was but a <hi>Caueat</hi> hereafter to beware how he gaue ſuch ſodaine entertainment to ſtrangers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A true and merry conceipt Ratſey performed vpon a Pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock that trauelled the Countries as a foot-poſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T chanced that as <hi>Ratſey</hi> rode abroad, he heard ſtill of a fellow that trauelled vp and downe the countrie, in the name and nature of a foot-poſt, with a long pikt ſtaffe on his necke, and a Leatherne bag ouerthwart his ſhoulder and vnder his arme, that protended to carry let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters too and fro, but in ſtéed of packets, his bag was fild with picklocks, and in euery Inne and Aſehouſe where he lodg'd all night, he paid the hoſtiſſe with her owne money, and carryed ſomewhat away beſides too, for there was not a Cupbord or Cheſt that he could come néere, but he would pick open, and if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re were no money in it, then money worth ſhould walke with him; and he would not ſticke to rob poore Milke-maids, and ſeruants towards an euening, if be met them handſomly, if they had not aboue ſixe pence in their purſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ratſey</hi> came in no place, but complaints were ſtill made of ſuch a fellow, and he did enuie the practiſes of ſuch deiect and baſe conditions, and reſolued in his minde if euer he met with him, both to redreſſe &amp; reuenge his villanies, &amp; to effect ſome matter of conceipt vpon him, that ſhould be worth talking, and deceiue the foot-poſt in his art of lock-picking.</p>
               <p>It chanced that not long after the foot-poſt came into an Inne in <hi>Stilton</hi> to drinke, where <hi>Ratſey</hi> was at dinner, who eſpying him out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſement of a window that ſtood open, (for he had certaine notice what kind a fellow he was, &amp; in what attire and faſhion he trauelled) he cauſd him to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in, and after ſome queſtions, <hi>Ratſey</hi> made him to drinke,
<pb facs="tcp:2718:15"/>and to ſit downe to dinner with <hi>Shorthoſe</hi> and <hi>Snell.</hi> They fild his veines with good victualles, and wine, &amp; that made the footpoſt very merry.</p>
               <p>I pray thee footpoſt (ſaies <hi>Ratſey</hi>) which way doſt thou trauell? faith Sir (ſaies he) I go euery way, euen as the directions of my letters giue me occaſion, But now I am going to Cambridge: I pray thee then quoth <hi>Ratſey,</hi> let me intreat thee to carry me a letter to the Iailor. For my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſent in a fellon thither the other day, and I ſhould ſend word to the Iaylour that hee ſhould not be bailed. Marry that I will in moſt dutifull manner (quoth this ſuppoſed footpoſt) and much more for your worſhip then that: Then <hi>Ratſey</hi> demaunded his name which he told him, Giue him a cuppe of wine (ſayes <hi>Ratſey:</hi> and while hee is drinking and at dinner I will write my letter, &amp; make it ready. But in ſtead of a letter <hi>Ratſey</hi> counterfeited a Iuſtice of peace his hand in Cambridge ſhire and wrote his <hi>Mittimus,</hi> and ſet it in with this <hi>Prouiſo,</hi> that he ſhould be kept faſt boulted or els he would breake away.</p>
               <p>As ſoone as the <hi>Mittimus</hi> was made, ſealed, and ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in forme of a letter, <hi>Ratſey</hi> deliuered it to the footpoſt, and ſaid giue this to the chiefe Iaylor of cambridge, and here is halfe a crowne for thee to drinke for thy labor. So the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt tooke the letter and the money, and with many a cappe and knee thanked <hi>Ratſey</hi> and departed. And made haſt till he came at Cambridge, and ſtaide not in the towne ſomuch as to taſt a cuppe of nappie Ale, before he came to the Iay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, and to him very briefely hee deliuered the letter, The Iaylour tooke it, and read it, and ſmilde a good, and ſayde, Footepoſt thou are welcome, for ſuch a Gentlemans ſake, He bids mee giue thee the beſt intertainment I may, I, Sir, quoth the Footpoſt, the Gentleman loues me well, and I thanke him for it, I dined well with his Men to day.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2718:15"/>
               <p>But I pray you (ſaies the footpoſt) hath the curteous Gentleman remembred ſuch a poore man as I am in his letter? I mary doth he (fellow) quoth he, and therefore Sirra (ſaith the Iaylor, and calls to one of his men) take the footpoſt into the loweſt ward, clappe a ſtrong paire of bolts vpon his heeles, and ſearch what other letters he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in his leatherne Caſket, which his man performing, found nothing in the ſame, but <hi>3.</hi> or <hi>4.</hi> bundels of picklocks, Then the Iaylor commaunded he ſhould haue a paire of ſhackles clapt on more, and bad him to ſee if his picklockes would ſerue his turne to baile him thence. But the footpoſt (or rather picklocke) hearing his <hi>Mittimus,</hi> was blanke and cold at heart, and had not a worde to ſay his Conſcience did ſo accuſe him. But there he lay while the next Seſſions and was hanged, for many matters did come againſt him.</p>
               <p>Now let true men iudge, what knauerie is amongſt Théeues when one croſſbites another to the Gallowes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How Ratſey robd a Preacher, by perſwaſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nother time <hi>Ratſey</hi> ryding by the way, vpon New Market heath, ouertooke a Preacher, vpon whom he intended to paſſe ſome pranke, and reſolued there could be no better ieſt practiſed vppon a Parſon then to picke his purſe by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, without drawing of any wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, And at the firſt gaue him this encounter. <hi>You are well ouertaken ſir. You are welcome</hi> ſayes the <hi>Preacher.</hi> Pray you how farre ride you this way quoth <hi>Ratſey,</hi> I ride ſayes the Preacher to ſuch a place: if you ride that way, I would be glad of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnay: yes indeed (anſwers <hi>Ratſey</hi>)
<pb facs="tcp:2718:16"/>that ſame waie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lies my buſineſſe, and I will accompanie you with all my heart. Thus their ſeuerall ſalutatons en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon their firſt meeting: they entered into further communication of diuers matters and ſo beguiled much time and way with ſuch talke, but that was not the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which <hi>Ratſey</hi> aymed at, for hee meant to giue the Churchman another text to preach vpon. Therefore fell roundly to his purpoſe in this faſhion. I perceaue Sir by your habit you are a Preacher, and Schollers both by art and nature are kind and curteous, I doe little therfore miſdoubte your friendly reſpect of what I ſhall ſpeake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you Know then that I am a Gentleman, and haue béene a man of better meanes then my preſent fortunes makes ſhew of; But by the fortunes of warre, and my owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order I am fallen into the hands of <hi>Extremity,</hi> and am forſt to lay my wants open to the helpe of others, and I thinke I cannot fitter communicate my griefes to any then a man of your condition, for you preach to others the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of good deedes and <hi>Charity,</hi> therefore I doubt not but your ſelfe will be reſpectiue of ſuch as are needye. I confeſſe I haue beene a great malefactor, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> am ſory for what is paſt and would willingly preuent any miſfortunes to come: Yet I was neuer neerer the mouth of miſhappe, then I am now at this inſtant, For my wants are ſuch, and ſo deſperate as if I haue it not of you, I muſt and will haue mony of him I méete next, although I hazard my déereſt blood. Therefore as you are a Gentleman, and a Scholler, tender my diſtreſſe: and conſider the force and powre of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> which conſtraines them that are nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to rod, and take away the goods of their neighbors, &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes to endanger their liues and limmes, &amp; ſo at laſt bring themſelues by ſuch lewd courſes to vntimely end. If I doe paſſe from you vnpitied and vnreleeued, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I thus make my minde and extremities knowne
<pb facs="tcp:2718:16"/>vnto you, and afterwards be conſtrained to fall into Theft, or murther, aſſure your ſelfe you are partaker of my euill, in that you haue not reduced me going awry, nor ſupported me being ready to fall.</p>
               <p>The Preacher was feelingly toucht with this paſſion, &amp; told him that he was inwardly grieued that a gentleman of his ranke and faſhion ſhould be driuen to ſo lowe an ebbe: and that his meanes could not anſwere his willing minde: And ſo drew his purſe out of his pocket, and ſaies to <hi>Ratſey</hi> heres mony, hold, take it, I thinke it be three pounds or thereabouts. I would I were better prouided to pleaſure you. <hi>Ratſey</hi> receaued it, and gaue him great thankes, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to ſound him déeper whether hee had any more ſtore or no. Therefore ſeconded his ſpéech in this manner. Sir quoth <hi>Ratſey,</hi> this is money indeed, and will ſerue a mans preſent occaſions for meat and drinke, but not to furniſh me to ſuch preferment as I am hopefull of: and my minde giues mee (I cannot tell what the reaſon is) that you haue more money about you, If you haue, it ill befits a man of your profeſſion to diſſemble, for that is a fault you much reprehend in others: Therefore as you will anſweare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, I charge you tell me the truth howſoeuer it bée: Why then (quoth the preacher) to deale plainly with you: I haue tenne poundes more which I receiued this Morning. Let me ſee it (ſaies <hi>Ratſey</hi>) So hee drew it out of his other pocket, and deliuered it to <hi>Ratſey:</hi> Who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning the purſe and thrée poundes backe to the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, kept the tenne pounds and told him, that (he thought) would ſerue his turne, and ſaue him from imminent daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that before he was ready to fall into. And (ſayes <hi>Ratſey</hi>) if euer my eſtate bée raiſed to that ability that I bee able, I pray you tell mée your name and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and I will make you vndoubted reſtitution for it,
<pb facs="tcp:2718:17"/>in the meane time I will but borrow this of you till my better fortunes. And ſo would haue taken his leaue and departed. Nay (ſayes the Preacher) I pray you leaue me not to night, but lie at mine Inne with me, and I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you (for all this) I will beare your charges, and be merry with you. Pardon me for that, ſayes <hi>Ratſey;</hi> ſo you may doe me wrong, and charge the Conſtable with me, and ſay I haue robd you of ten pound, when I haue but borrowed it: I dare not hazard my life and liberty ſo ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly. As I am an honeſt man, ſayes the Preacher, and looke for mercy at Gods hands at the laſt day, beléeue me I will not ſpeake one word of it to any man, neither ſhall you be troubled or iniured any way by my meanes or procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for I am ſo well perſwaded of you, that if you liue, you will one day giue it me againe.</p>
               <p>Vpon this religious proteſtation, <hi>Ratſey</hi> rode along with him, and ſet vp their horſes together, ſupt together, and lay together. For <hi>Ratſey</hi> handled his talke, and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſo orderly in the preſence of the Preacher, that he conceiued an extraordinary good opinion of him, and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the former accident to neceſſitie, rather then the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of <hi>Ratſeys</hi> condition.</p>
               <p>The morning being come, they brake their faſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Parſon payd all according to promiſe, and <hi>Ratſey</hi> brought him ten miles of his way, where they tooke their ſeuerall leaues. <hi>Ratſey</hi> with redoubled thanks, and promiſe to pay the money againe, and the Preacher with a world of good counſell, for (ſayes he) if that may ſerue to ſaue you from ſuch perrill as you pretended, I ſhall thinke it the moſt charitable déed that euer I did in my life. And ſo they parted.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2718:17"/>
               <head>A true relation of the Robbery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted by <hi>Ratſey</hi> and his company, within a little off <hi>Bedford,</hi> for which they were Executed at <hi>Bedford</hi> the 27. of March laſt. 1605.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Gentleman, and his Brother dwelling within ſixe or ſeauen miles of <hi>Bedford,</hi> hauing bin in a place where they had receaued the ſumme of eight ſcore and fourteene poundes, or there abouts, <hi>Ratſey</hi> had ſecret knowledge and intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence thereof, and of the way which they trauelled homewards: So both he, and <hi>Snell,</hi> and <hi>Shorthoſe</hi> dog'd both the Gentlemen, whereof the one carried the money before him in a Wallet, &amp; could ſpie no conuenient place to giue onſet to their purpoſe, til they came within halfe a mile of the Gentlemans owne houſe: Then <hi>Ratſey</hi> (by his intelligence) thought it was either high time to ſtrike or to deſiſt from their former reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for by the notice that was giuen him, he knew be was not far from the Gentlemans groundes, and place of dwelling. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being well horſt (for hee was vppon the Coniurers Gelding he toucht him with his ſpurres and ſoone ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke the Gentleman. To whome hee briefely began to tell the cauſe of his comming, which was (he ſaid for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and money hee muſt haue. The Gentleman told him that he wold not part with his money ſo eaſily and alighted and <hi>Ratſey</hi> and he betooke themſelues to their weapons, and while they were at it, verie luſtilye, the Gentlemans brother began to ride away with the money, but <hi>Sne</hi> I followed him and ſoone brought him againe, who kept him ſafe while the other were fighting who ſhould carrie away the money. The Gentleman is knowne in his Countrie to bee verie ſtout and valiant, and had not his ſword broken, it is thought that <hi>Ratſey</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2718:18"/>and <hi>Snell</hi> both could not haue rob'd him, (for <hi>Shorthoſe</hi> neuer came in.) The Gentleman hurt <hi>Ratſey</hi> verie dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly, and he himſelfe had a maime in his leg, which is ſaid to be done by <hi>Snell</hi> comming in to aide <hi>Ratſey,</hi> and beeing both vppon him, when the Gentlemans ſword failed, the money was deliuered, and with much danger <hi>Ratſey</hi> and his companions eſcaped, for hue &amp; crie went foorth in euerie place, but they ſpared no Horſe-fleſh till they Coaſted the Countrie and came to <hi>Saffron-walden,</hi> there one of them had ſome friendes or Kinsfolkes, with whome they all repoſed themſelues a day or two, and <hi>Snell</hi> and <hi>Shorthoſe</hi> did there change away their horſes.</p>
               <p>From thence they tooke their ſeueral courſes to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, where they met altogether in an Inne in South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke, where it is reported they ſhared their money, and that <hi>Ratſey</hi> had two ſhares allowed him in reſpect of his hurts receaued.</p>
               <p>But as goods euil got, are for the moſte part euill ſpent: ſo they made as little conſcience in conſuming their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as they did in getting the ſame. And as deceipt hath ſtil his due, and God is iuſt in punniſhing offendors, ſo fell it out in their ſeueral apprehenſions, for <hi>Snel</hi> being taken in Duck-lane in London for a Horſe that hee had ſtolne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> about Graueſ-end, not for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> robbery commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Bedford-ſhire,</hi> &amp; being examined before a Iuſtice, &amp; readie to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to priſon, he appealed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iuſtice for fauour, lolde him hee would helpe him to one <hi>Ratſey</hi> of whome ſuch fame went for many robberies, if he weld be good vnto him for his life. The Iuſtice promiſed him his lawful fauor, &amp; therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Snell</hi> gaue him notice where <hi>Ratſeys</hi> Horſe ſtood, and where hee ſhould haue him. So by his directions <hi>Ratſey</hi> was taken, and apprehended neere the Doctors Commons and committed to New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,
<pb facs="tcp:2718:18"/>where he remained a long time, and <hi>Snell</hi> likewiſe. In which ſpace, two or thee Seſſions paſt, &amp; they neuer call'd to any triall.</p>
               <p>All this while <hi>Shorthoſe</hi> was at libertie, and hauing been vp and downe in the Countrie, fiue or ſixe weekes, and comming to London to liſten how <hi>Ratſey</hi> and <hi>Snell</hi> had ſped the Seſſions before, he went and vnfoulded his minde to one <hi>Water Skellington</hi> a Countrieman of his, who reuealed him to the keepers of Newgate, and ſo hee was likewiſe apprehended in Long-lane, in the liberties of great S. <hi>Bartholmewes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So beeing thus ſeuerally taken, Newgate held and contained them till <hi>Snell</hi> deſired the Iuſtice to remooue him to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kings Bench, for feare leaſt one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſhold doe him ſome ſuddaine miſchiefe for reuealing of <hi>Ratſey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A little before the Aſſize time in Lent laſt, they were all remooued downe to <hi>Bedford,</hi> where they had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained long, but <hi>Ratſey</hi> had eaten off his Irons with a water which hee had gotten, and ſo had eſcaped, but that hee was eſpyed in time, and preuented by the Keeper.</p>
               <p>To bee ſhort, the Aſſizes being come, they were all brought downe to the place of Iudgement, where they ſhewed themſelues ſo valiant that they thruſt twelue men into a corner, who ſound them all guiltie for the Robberie committed in <hi>Bedfordſhire</hi> vppon the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and his Brother. And they were ſent away from the Barre with the dolefull ſentence of <hi>Lord haue mercie vpon you.</hi> And the ſeauen and twentie day of March laſt, they were all Executed in <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="repentance">
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:19"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Ratſeys repentance which he wrote</hi> with his owne hand when hee was <hi>in New-gate.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe ſilent night had ſhadowed euerie Tree,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Phoebus</hi> in the weſt was ſhrowded lowe:</l>
               <l>Each Hiue had home her buſie labouring Bee,</l>
               <l>And Birds their nightly harbour gan to knowe.</l>
               <l>And all things did from wearie labour linne,</l>
               <l>When I began to way my ſtate and ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Men worne with worke betooke them to their reſt,</l>
               <l>The ſunne had left to ſhew his glorious beames:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Titan</hi> had fully hid him in the Weſt,</l>
               <l>To coole the ſet lockes of his wearie teames;</l>
               <l>When ſunke with ſorrow beeing captiuate,</l>
               <l>I ſhed foorth teares, lamenting much my ſtate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My head on hand, my elboe on my knee,</l>
               <l>And teares did trickle downe my count<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nance than,</l>
               <l>My countenance as ſad as mans might bee,</l>
               <l>My dumps befitting well a captiue man.</l>
               <l>Fetter'd in Priſon, paſſionate alone.</l>
               <l>My ſighs wrought teares, and thus I gan to moane.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:19"/>
            <lg>
               <l>I that of late did liue a Souldiers life,</l>
               <l>And ſpent my ſeruice in my countries good,</l>
               <l>Now captiue lie, where nought but cares are rife,</l>
               <l>Where is no hope but loſſe of deereſt blood,</l>
               <l>This is befall'n mee, cauſe I did miſpend,</l>
               <l>That time which God to better vſe did lend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sigh! for my muſicke is a Syrens ſong,</l>
               <l>A faire deceipt, to ſhadow men in griefe:</l>
               <l>Did I ſay fayre? Alas I call'd it wrong,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes</hi> knew the <hi>Syrens</hi> daungers chiefe,</l>
               <l>Was when ſhe ſung to lull a man a ſleepe,</l>
               <l>Then faſhion'd ſhee to ſing, to make men weepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Deceauing <hi>Syrens, Syrens</hi> all to mee,</l>
               <l>A ſhining ſhadowe, but a dreame of glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de:</l>
               <l>A bayte, a trappe: I blinde and could not ſee,</l>
               <l>A dangerous pray, and I both fond and bolde.</l>
               <l>Would venture all, all for a worthles toye,</l>
               <l>And ſo I left, and loſt my chiefeſt ioye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Had I but ſtopt mine eares when <hi>Syrens</hi> ſung</l>
               <l>And bound my ſelfe vnto <hi>Vliſſes</hi> maſt:</l>
               <l>Or had I thought, alas I am but young,</l>
               <l>Too much is all to venture on a caſt.</l>
               <l>I might haue liu'd, and from all dangers free,</l>
               <l>Where now I dye, for life is not for me.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:20"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But I did follow what I knew was vaine,</l>
               <l>Inſteed of vertue, I did vice imbrace:</l>
               <l>My former pleaſures now procure my paine,</l>
               <l>And cauſe I lackt one ſparke of timely grace.</l>
               <l>The poyſoned <hi>Aconite</hi> of death and woe,</l>
               <l>Reſolues to ſend a fatall ouerthrowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This makes mines eyes to guſh out floods of teares,</l>
               <l>My fleſh to melt, my vaines and artirs rend:</l>
               <l>My ſoule to ſeeke redreſſe, to cure her feares,</l>
               <l>For now my cauſe cannot affoord one friend.</l>
               <l>I that of late did number many friends,</l>
               <l>Nowe finde them fled, and no man comfort lends.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The leaueles tree with wrath of Winters winde</l>
               <l>Beſt repreſents my wretched waſting ſtate:</l>
               <l>Fortune the winde, the leaues my friends I finde,</l>
               <l>My ſelfe the Tree that thus am croſt by fate.</l>
               <l>And yet in this we greatly differ may,</l>
               <l>That it reuiues and I ſtill pine away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I cannot ſpeake but kill my ſelfe with words,</l>
               <l>I cannot thinke, but I my conſcience wounde:</l>
               <l>Law ſtabbes me ſtill, in euery part with ſwords,</l>
               <l>Iuſtice commaunds in fetters I bee bound,</l>
               <l>And for I haue been graceles, griefes doe ſpring,</l>
               <l>My daies miſled, my preſent cares doe bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:20"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Confounding ſadnes like a loade of leade,</l>
               <l>Chilles all my blood, and makes my ſinewes ſhrinke,</l>
               <l>Reuenge (quoth wrong) let rigour ſtand in ſtead,</l>
               <l>Death filles the Cup, and ſaies that I muſt drinke.</l>
               <l>This makes me pleade, this makes me call and cry</l>
               <l>To heauens great King for mercie ere I die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I all confuſ'd and in confuſion wrapt,</l>
               <l>Implore Gods mercy, proſtrate on my face:</l>
               <l>Youngling I was, and nouice-like intrapt,</l>
               <l>Repentance true, away ſhall follies chaſe.</l>
               <l>Forgiue, Oh heauens th'iniquities of youth,</l>
               <l>Doe not obiect the faults of my vntruth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Villaines avaunt, you baſtards are by kinde,</l>
               <l>That doe perturbe the Countries quiet ſtate,</l>
               <l>Shame to offend, ſhun a corrupted minde,</l>
               <l>And learne by me your former life to hate.</l>
               <l>Liue of your owne, and braue it not with brags.</l>
               <l>Leaſt Law condemne you in your proudeſt rags.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Awake for ſhame, and lift your eye-lids vp,</l>
               <l>Sleepe not ſecure, nor dreame of doing wrong,</l>
               <l>If Iuſtice ſtrike, you cannot change her cup,</l>
               <l>Death being done, you fall, for he is ſtrong.</l>
               <l>And then your courſe, becauſe you did not ceaſe</l>
               <l>To vexe your King, with noubling countries peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:21"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Drinke not the <hi>Nectar</hi> of your Neighbors ſweate,</l>
               <l>Steale not at all, thy God dooth ſo commaund:</l>
               <l>Whoſe lawe to keepe thy Sou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raigne doth intreate,</l>
               <l>Thy health it is, Gods law to vnderſtand;</l>
               <l>Obeying God, God ſhall all harmes preuent,</l>
               <l>Keeping Kings Peace, thy King is well content.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Like to the Woolfe in euerie place you range,</l>
               <l>Praying on Lambes that neuer went aſtray:</l>
               <l>And like Camelions muſt your ſuites be ſtrange,</l>
               <l>Who dooth by kinde change colours euery day;</l>
               <l>Without reſpect, forgetting what you bee,</l>
               <l>Masking in ſinne, as if God could not ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Abate preſumption, ſinne is not a ieſt,</l>
               <l>Though God forbeare, yet will he ſtrike at length,</l>
               <l>God made thee man, make not thy ſelfe a beaſt,</l>
               <l>But ſeeke to loue thy God with ſoule and ſtrength.</l>
               <l>Ill got ill ſpent, your hopes (in Theft) pretended,</l>
               <l>Are griefe and ſhame, and life in ſorrowes ended.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Your chiefe deſires to fill your purſſe with golde,</l>
               <l>By hooke and crooke all careles of regarde;</l>
               <l>You count him beſt that <hi>Bayardlike</hi> is bolde,</l>
               <l>For ſuch deſires, ſharpe reckonining is prep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rde.</l>
               <l>Leaue then to ſinne, ſo may you ſcape that fall:</l>
               <l>Which following vice, you cannot ſhun at all.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:21"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Mad is the minde, that ſtill in dangers ſtray,</l>
               <l>Iron his heart, whoſe gaine is others woe:</l>
               <l>Solde is his ſoule, whome <hi>Sathan</hi> leades away,</l>
               <l>His path diſtruction, where ſo ere he goe,</l>
               <l>Solde, ſolde, for droſſe: Oh bee not ſo deceau'd!</l>
               <l>Hell gapes, ſoule ſincks, of heauenly ioyes bereau'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It's I inuect, knowes what infection is,</l>
               <l>And loues effect, that makes me thus to warne:</l>
               <l>Take what I giue for good confection tis,</l>
               <l>By my downe-fall far better may you learne,</l>
               <l>Leaſt all to late, you weepe as well as I,</l>
               <l>In deathes deepe griefe, expecting ſtill to die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My ſorrowing ſobbes with teares redeeme what's paſt.</l>
               <l>Or ſlouds of teares ſuffice for fore-done ills:</l>
               <l>Beholde my lookes with diſcontent ore caſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe heart dooth rend, whoſe eyes freſh fountaines ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ls,</l>
               <l>And yet all this, and all that I can doe,</l>
               <l>Is ſmall to that, which I haue neede to doe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My ſoule ſhall mourne for all my ill-done deedes,</l>
               <l>And I will weepe, ſole Author of ſoules woe:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Repentance</hi> ſhall be my blacke mourning weedes,</l>
               <l>Ile bathe my ſelfe in teares from top to toe.</l>
               <l>And while life is, which cannot now belong,</l>
               <l>Graunt mercie Lord, this ſhall be all my ſong.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:22"/>
            <lg>
               <l>My heart through fleſh ſhall iſſue ſweating griefe,</l>
               <l>And ſcald my bones, with ſalt and briniſh teares:</l>
               <l>Through fleſh and bone my heart ſhall beg reliefe,</l>
               <l>On bended knees, till bone my fleſh outweares.</l>
               <l>All that I am, Ile ſpend in mourne for ſinne,</l>
               <l>And where I end, a freſh I will begin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Deuine celeſtiall maker of earths Globe,</l>
               <l>Crown'd King of Kings, moſte happie power of powers:</l>
               <l>Iuſt in thy Iudgement, cleare in Scarlet Robe,</l>
               <l>Sweet of all ſweets, in iudgement gall to ſowres.</l>
               <l>Releaſe my ſorrowes, if thou thinke it meete,</l>
               <l>And Salue my ſinfull ſores with Balme ſo ſweet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great God, remit the follies of my youth,</l>
               <l>Thy power deuine, I will no more offend,</l>
               <l>But I will ſtriue to ſerue thee ſtill in truth,</l>
               <l>While to this bodie thou a life doſt lend,</l>
               <l>And at my end, Ile giue the praiſe to thee,</l>
               <l>If thou but graunt one dram of thy mercie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If <hi>Maudlins</hi> teares did euer <hi>Chriſt's</hi> feete wet,</l>
               <l>And ſweet her ſoule with true repentant teares:</l>
               <l>If <hi>Peters</hi> mourning ſtreames did mercy get,</l>
               <l>For all his ſinnes, though hee his <hi>Chriſt</hi> forſweares.</l>
               <l>My ſad laments abounding from mine eyes,</l>
               <l>Sweet God accept, and heare my mournefull cryes.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:22"/>
            <lg>
               <l>A wounded Soule, a broken contrite heart,</l>
               <l>Creepes in great'ſt throng thy mercies Throne to touch,</l>
               <l>The oyle of life, King of my life impart,</l>
               <l>Though ſinne be great, thy mercies thrice as much.</l>
               <l>Oh thou that art in power, and mercy great!</l>
               <l>Send downe thy mercie, from thy mercies feate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Publican</hi> ſuppreſt with weight of ſinne,</l>
               <l>Durſt not preſume to caſt his eyes on hie,</l>
               <l>Gazing on earth his heart did neuer linne,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Miſerere</hi> lowely he did crie.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Peccaui</hi> Lord, this ſinners ſoule confeſſed.</l>
               <l>Whoſe note I ſing that haue no leſſe tranſgreſſed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The wandring Sonne, whoſe portion was miſpent,</l>
               <l>With ryots, ſurfets quaffing bowles of wine,</l>
               <l>Dainties all deere: In hunger now content,</l>
               <l>To feede with Hogs this prodigalls not nice.</l>
               <l>All tattered torne ſhak't out of colours fine,</l>
               <l>Neede him compels to keepe a ſtrangers ſwine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ground contentes him now to reſt vpon,</l>
               <l>Whome beds of downe did whilome diſcontent,</l>
               <l>His head vp boulſtred with ſome hill or ſtone,</l>
               <l>The clouds a couering to his field-bed lent,</l>
               <l>Where ſorrie man ore' plundged wofull lyes,</l>
               <l>His Curtaines colde, his Canapy the skies.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:23"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Renumerating with himſelfe the cauſe.</l>
               <l>Of want, of woe, of hunger and of colde:</l>
               <l>Offence to God, the breaking of his lawes,</l>
               <l>Then breake out teares, he could no longer holde,</l>
               <l>But weeping ran, till he his Father ſees,</l>
               <l>In true repentance, bending on his knees.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And with lowd Organ of a faynting ſoule,</l>
               <l>Father, (he ſaid) I haue gainſt heauen offended,</l>
               <l>Gainſt earth and thee, whoſe power dooth ſin controule<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>No worthy Sonne: ſo he his faint ſpeech ended.</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill in ſilence, pearles of teares dril'd foorth,</l>
               <l>Till Fathers welcome counted him of worth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His Fathers heart in pittie then relents,</l>
               <l>About his necke he cloſde his aged armes:</l>
               <l>Glad in his heart, his Sonne in heart repents,</l>
               <l>Receaues him home, and with a kiſſe he warnes,</l>
               <l>That all his friendes ſhould feaſt at his free coſt,</l>
               <l>And welcome home his Sonne, ſo long was loſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thrice happie Sonne, whoſe teares renew this grace,</l>
               <l>And ſweet repentance was it home thee brought:</l>
               <l>Threefolde, thrice double, happie Fathers face,</l>
               <l>A Sonne to finde whome thou ſo long haſt ſought.</l>
               <l>And Sonne moſte happie in a Father kinde,</l>
               <l>Who being loſt, did ſuch a Father finde.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:23"/>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſelfe ſame Balme, is cure for my great woe,</l>
               <l>The ſame repentance makes me <hi>Abba</hi> crie:</l>
               <l>My ſpeech dooth faint, and I can ſay no more,</l>
               <l>Mercye redreſſe, els languiſhing I die.</l>
               <l>Sweet, ſweete of ſweetes, bleſt balme, chiefe eaſe of paine,</l>
               <l>Graunt memy home, I will not ſtray againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No more ſhall folly holde my wits in thrall,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wiſdome</hi> ſhall ranſome <hi>Will</hi> from <hi>Follies</hi> bandes,</l>
               <l>Experience ſhall forewarne me <hi>Syrens</hi> all,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall diſpaire, touch <hi>Conſcience</hi> with foule hands;</l>
               <l>But till lifes end, my prayers to heauen ſhall hye,</l>
               <l>And with repentance will I liue, and die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With ſinne my ſoule ſhall bee no more oppreſt,</l>
               <l>My God to ſerue ſhall now be all my care:</l>
               <l>No longer ſhall my thoughts bee at vnreſt,</l>
               <l>But dayly ſhun the place where wicked are.</l>
               <l>And while the remnant of my life doth laſt,</l>
               <l>Ile ſigh, and ſorrow for my ſinnes forepaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My colour'd ſuites I now exchange for blacke,</l>
               <l>Till ſcarlet ſinnes be all as white as ſnowe:</l>
               <l>On me ſweet time ſhall neuer turne his backe,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall his taske be more my tares to mowe,</l>
               <l>But with repentance, furrow hopes forlorne,</l>
               <l>Till God giue grace, I ſheaff vp better corne.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2718:24"/>
            <lg>
               <l>This little remnant of my life ſo poore.</l>
               <l>He teach to ſhun all ſinne and vices all,</l>
               <l>Giuer of grace, graunt grace I ſinne no more,</l>
               <l>Eſtabliſh me that I may neuer fall,</l>
               <l>To thee my heart, my life and ſoule I giue,</l>
               <l>Who after death eternally makes liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Dyrect my pathes euen for thy mercies ſake,</l>
               <l>Guide thou my ſteps, to keepe repentant wayes:</l>
               <l>Keepe me from ſleept, in thee ſtill let me wake,</l>
               <l>To laude thy name, during theſe arthly daies.</l>
               <l>And when from earth I ſhall diſsolue to iuſt,</l>
               <l>Graunt that my ſoule may liue among the juſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <signed>Gamaliel Ratſey.</signed>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
